Today I was looking at all of the the
banner headlines about the failure
yesterday uh in Alaska. The failure
because we didn't launch World War III
because the two presidents had a good
meeting together because they announced
progress. Uh this was is taken as
failure in our media which of course is
uh
hawkish by the moment and
uh manipulated by controlled by paid by
or simply aligned with the
military-industrial complex in the
country. So, it's extraordinarily hard
to hear a word about peace in this
country.
It's not so complicated actually to end
these conflicts. It's a little
surprising how long it takes and how
hard it is uh to to accomplish this, but
it's not so hard in substance because
the underlying reasons for the conflicts
that the United States is in perpetually
uh are not sound reasons from the point
of view of America's interests, from the
point of view of our security, from the
point of view of our well-being or our
econ economy. Uh all of the conflicts
that we are in and those that we could
get in are misguided,
misdirected,
provoked by us to a very large extent
and um solvable.
That's the basic point. It really is not
so complicated.
I think uh the wisest words which we
repeat and uh Dan just started us with
uh that we've heard in
the 80 years since the end of World War
II were those in President Eisenhower's
farewell address on January 17th,
1961. And I'll just repeat them because
they summarize all that has come to
pass. He said, "In the councils of
government, we must guard against the
acquisition of unwarranted influence,
whether sought or unsought, by the
military-industrial complex.
The potential for the disastrous rise of
misplaced power, exists and will
persist."
This is a man who knew what he was
talking about. as the Supreme Allied
Commander
and as president of the United States
and I might add as president of Columbia
University, his most important job. Uh
he he knew what he was talking about and
he was reporting to us a reality that
existed already in January 1961.
That reality almost led to the end of
the world actually. Uh just a year and a
half later in the Cuban missile crisis,
President Kennedy experienced the full
nearly catastrophic weight of the
military-industrial complex at that
time. Because if President Kennedy had
followed the overwhelming advice of
absolutely almost every advisor in that
XCOM that was famously preserved for
history through its recordings of the
days of that crisis, we would not be
here today.
And I think people know or you should
know that even after Kennedy and Kruev
resolved the crisis through a kind of
genius of decency and humanity against
the advice of all of their
military adviserss. We nearly had the
world end anyway because of a disabled
soviet submarine that was out of
communication. And when it began and it
was uh in crisis and when it began to
surface, some jackass in the US military
was dropping live hand grenades as a
joke rather than death charges. They
thought they were under attack. And it
happened to be the one submarine in the
squadron that had nuclear tipped
torpedoes and they were entered into the
bay and a man named Mr. Aripov
who was senior to the captain
countermanded the order and saved the
world only to go back home by the way
and be reprimanded uh and uh live in
obscurity. But literally the man who
saved the world uh saved the world
within 1 second because US doctrine at
the time was that any attack by a a
nuclear atomic weapon would be met by
the full force of the US nuclear
uh armaments. Uh and the estimation at
the time was 700 million dead across the
Soviet Union, China, uh Eastern Europe.
but good reason to believe that all of
humanity might have perished. And we
came within a second of that.
Uh next year, Kennedy made peace with
the Soviet Union in one of the most
brilliant and uh illustrative uh
episodes of modern history. I commend
everybody to uh listen to Kennedy's
peace speech of June 10, 1963.
My poor family has had to listen to it
maybe a hundred times. I wrote a book
about it because I loved the speech so
much. I was a friend also of Ted
Sorenson whom I admired enormously. But
Kennedy made peace by praising the
Soviet Union at the height of the Cold
War, talking about their valor, their
culture, their scientific
accomplishments, and the fact that both
sides would perish in a conflict so both
sides could be depended on to seek
peace. and Kruev
uh heard the speech immediately summoned
Kennedy's
envoy Averil Heramman and said that's
the finest speech by a modern American
president. I want to make peace with
your boss. And five weeks later, the
partial nuclear testban treaty was uh
signed. And about four months after
that, uh in my opinion, the CIA killed
Kennedy uh for that and for other crimes
of uh trying to make peace. Maybe that
explains the military-industrial complex
as much as anything. Maybe our leaders
are just afraid. Uh they're afraid to
make peace. They're afraid to step out
of line. Maybe it is true, as some have
said, that since John F. Kennedy, there
hasn't been a president really that has
been an independent actor in the
American scene. I think it's an arguably
correct point. Nixon is a another
partial example, and he may have paid
the price as well by an inside job to
help bring him down.
I think it's arguable that they're just
afraid. If they're not afraid of that,
maybe they're afraid of Mossad.
Or maybe they're bought.
Or maybe they don't understand. Or maybe
they read the New York Times.
It's a little hard to understand
why it is that we are in this mess of
war after war that cost trillions of
dollars
and that do nothing but worsen our
security.
I happen to be a fan of the Doomsday
Clock, which is the graphic of the
bulletin of atomic scientists unveiled
in 1947,
which tries to alert us with a
considered opinion of how close or far
we are from nuclear war and nuclear
Armageddon.
And as people who followed the doomsday
clock will know that when it was
unveiled in 1947, it was 7 minutes from
midnight.
It went closer to midnight during the
height of the cold war. Then as
some measure of gay tant uh and
Kennedy's initiatives
uh came to fruition, it was moved away
from midnight. Then it came closer to
midnight. Then the Cold War ended in
December 1991, or so we thought, and the
clock was reset at 17 minutes away from
midnight, the farthest away.
Every president since 1991
has been in a period in which the clock
has moved closer to midnight. I would
argue that every president since 1991,
Clinton, Bush Jr., Obama, Trump won,
Biden,
have moved us closer to disaster. That
this isn't just an accident of their
term. We had all of the ability to make
peace in 1991.
We chose not to. We chose not to
consciously.
The military-industrial complex and the
lobbies, the Israel lobby and others
chose not to. They chose not to because
they said after 1991, we are all
powerful and now we can do what we want.
And some of our so-called leaders and
strategists put it exactly in those
terms. Wolawitz and others who had the
doctrine that now we can do whatever we
want. We can go to war anywhere we want.
We can overthrow any government anywhere
we want. I had a bit of a front row seat
in those days because I uh fruitlessly
was trying to get the United States to
actually help the Soviet Union actively
in 1990 and then to help Russia in 1991
and 1992
with financial assistance because of an
urgent financial crisis that engulfed
not uh randomly but a failed economic
system but when a system fails and a
society is in distress
I believe you help so that you don't get
into worse trouble so I had a front row
seat I was part of an effort uh with as
an adviser to President Gorbachev
to try to enlist US support for
financial stabilization in a very deep
crisis
Then I was asked by President Yelen and
I mentioned this. I actually was in the
Kremlin on December I think it's
December 13. I haven't been able to
absolutely uh confirm the specific date,
but it was around December 13, 1991
when President Yeltson walked across the
room and sat in front of me because I
was a young kid but happened to be head
of the delegation and he said,
"Gentlemen, because it was all men, uh,
I want to tell you the Soviet Union is
over."
That's pretty interesting to hear that
in the Kremlin. I kind of pinched myself
and then it was my turn to speak and I
said, "Mr. President, this is one of the
greatest days in modern history and I am
sure I am sure that my country will come
to your assistance to give you help to
help you stabilize because I know how
extreme the financial crisis is. I'm a
financial economist. I've helped
stabilize a number of hyperinflations.
You need some urgent help, even just a
standstill on debt service payments
because you don't have foreign exchange
reserves. This is a revolution. You need
help to stabilize. But Mr. President,
I'm sure that this will happen.
Incidentally,
without digressing, I had said the same
thing as Poland's advisor two years
earlier. And when I made those
recommendations as a technical
economist, Brent Skraftoft, General
Skroft delivered within eight hours the
recommendations that I made and Senator
Dole. So I thought I'm a pretty good
economist, very convincing, uh, and
they'll do the same. Nothing of the
sort.
Then I got blamed for the lack of
stabilization in Russia by many people
though it was exactly the opposite of
what I had been saying because we
refused to provide any help whatsoever
and honestly I could not quite figure it
out.
I knew that the people weren't very
clever
but I still couldn't figure out why.
To summarize, the reason why is that the
cold war did not end in December 1991.
It was only midway.
Because the idea, which actually goes
back to the British, I would date it to
1840,
was to destroy Russia,
then to destroy the Soviet Union, and
then back again. Now we'll destroy
Russia.
And Brjinski spelled it out, of course,
in his book in 1997, The Grand
Chessboard, opining that a NATO
expansion eastward
would be inevitable that Russia would
exceed. What could it do? He actually
has a whole chapter reasoning that
Russia would never side with China.
Impossible, Zigg told us.
And I liked Big because he was a nice
man who helped me when I was helping
Poland.
But he had his designs. We're going to
break Russia.
And that's what the military-industrial
complex went after after 1991.
Another not so gentle gentleman
joined the scene in 1996.
another disaster of our time and that's
Benjamin Netanyahu.
One of the most vile
misguided
criminals on our planet as far as I'm
concerned.
Maybe you'll give me 58 standing
ovations like Congress gave Netanyahu 58
standing ovations.
But Netanyahu's idea was
at a at a smaller scale while the
military-industrial complex of Wolawitz
and Feith and all these extraordinarily
naive and ignorant people thought the US
would run the world. Israel decided, of
course, it would control the Middle
East, and it would do so on our tab and
with our military and with our support.
And so Netanyahu said, "We're not going
to make any compromises."
It's even a funny term if you know the
history of Zionism that it's a
compromise. Uh we come in, you should
leave, uh is is the basic summary. But
not even we'll divide the house. It was
your house. We'll divide the house.
We'll take 78%, you can have 22%. No,
we'll take 100% and there's a lot of
places you can move to. What are you
complaining about? You ingrate.
That's the basis of the idea. And then
the point is that a lot of people won't
like that. there will be uh there will
be a militant reaction and then
Netanyahu's idea is you don't fight the
militants, you fight the governments
that backed them. So we know of course
from Wesley Clark the famous story that
he visited the Pentagon a week after
9/11 and he was shown the list of the
seven wars in five years which was a
neocon Israel concoction combined. We're
going to take out all those governments
and that is Lebanon, Syria, Iraq, Iran,
Somalia, Sudan, and Libya.
You know what? We've been at war with
all seven of them.
It didn't quite go to plan of seven wars
in five years
because we got bogged down in each one.
It didn't go to plan because it made a
wasteland of several thousand kilometers
from Libya to Iran.
But that's been a plan
and that's part of this same disaster.
It solves nothing. We have solved
nothing. And to this day, these
maniacs
in who are murderous genocide
and killing in mass murder. To this day,
they have the backing of the United
States government. Not even a murmur of
opposition.
60,000 dead, 20,000 of them or 18,000 by
the official count. children, names
listed in the Washington Post recently,
people showing up starving at food
depots to be shot at,
all caught on Tik Tok.
Ben Gavir saying, "We're going to take
everything again yesterday." Not a
murmur from our government. Who runs it?
What is going on? the American people at
least 2 to1 against Israel in this in
the opinion surveys because the American
public is revolted by what's happening.
So this is why we're here
and
yesterday was a at least a glimmer of
hope. It's just a glimmer. There's a
battle going on obviously in Washington
and in London. London is even worse than
Washington by the way because they had
centuries of insanity.
If anyone's here from Britain, my
apologies,
but it's unbelievable. It shows you can
lose your empire 80 years ago and still
think you have it and still think you
run the world and still think that
America's your junior partner doing your
mischief. MI6 is an absolute reckless
out of control disaster and you look at
a
starmer.
Oh my god, don't get me started.
Do not get me started because I will not
get off the podium.
Uh we had a doctrine
issued 202 years ago which is not
remembered properly, the Monroe
Doctrine. And I do want to remember it
because it's
sometimes taken as a bogeyman or
sometimes taken as a statement of
American foreign policy, but it's not
taken correctly.
And the idea of the Monroe Doctrine was
that in the aftermath of the Napoleonic
Wars and the Declaration of Independence
of the other states in the Western
Hemisphere in the early years of the
1820s, the United States said to the
European powers, "Do not interfere in
our hemisphere."
Okay. Little bold by the way of the US
at the time. We were not exactly the
strapping empire of the world compared
to the European empires. But there was
actually a very important part of it
that I want to recall and I want to read
it and I quote, it's from the message to
Congress of President Monroe December
2nd, 1823
with this part written by the Secretary
of State John Quincy Adams. He said,
"Our policy in regard to Europe, which
was adopted at an early stage of the
wars that have so long agitated that
quarter of the globe, nevertheless
remains the same, which is not to
interfere in the internal concerns of
any of its powers."
It was a reciprocal commitment. Stay out
of our lane, we'll stay out of your
lane.
This is really smart advice.
even smarter in a nuclear armed world.
Don't go to provoke.
Don't think you run the world.
Don't expand NATO eastward to you to
Russia's border for God's sake
after you have said repeatedly
explicitly not ambiguously
to President Gorbachav and to other
Soviet and Russian leaders that NATO
would not move one inch eastward. And if
you think it's a myth, go to the
National Security Archive of George
Washington University and pull out the
dozens of documents
or the clips of Hans Dietra Genture
saying explicitly, this doesn't refer to
a promise within Germany. This is in
general, we're not going to move
eastward.
That's what the Monroe Doctrine really
says.
What are we doing?
Trying to push NATO
to Ukraine and to Georgia. Well, I'll
tell you what we're doing. We're doing
what Lord Palmerston tried to do in 1853
in the Crimean War, which was to
surround Russia and banish Russia from
the Black Sea. That's the idea. And
immediately after the Maidon coup, which
my colleague Victoria Nuland was a very
competent uh sponsor of, she now teaches
diplomacy at Columbia University.
You cannot make this up. Even George
Orwell did not imagine such a thing.
Anyway, she teaches diplomacy together
with Hillary Clinton.
It's so weird. Anyway, uh the coup came
and immediately the postcool government
said we don't think the Russians should
be in Crimea. That is their naval base
for the last hundred from 1783. I won't
calculate the number of years.
That was the idea. It was Palmerston's
idea. It was Bjinsk's idea.
That's not the Monroe Doctrine. That is
we will be in your face right up to your
face. We will annoy you. We will, as the
Rand Corporation
wrote in 2019 in one of the most absurd,
dangerous, ridiculous exemplars of
American foreign policy, "We will extend
you." extending Russia. A document of a
think tank how to annoy Russia in 27
different ways. Is this really what we
pay them for? How to provoke the other
nuclear superpower with 6,000 nuclear
weapons and then wonder why the hand of
the doomsday clock is 89 seconds to
midnight?
These people are crazy.
Honestly, it's very very dangerous.
So, I know I don't nobody told me how
long to speak and I tend to speak about
six hours. Uh so, I'm going to stop uh
uh very shortly.
Let me just say that all the major
conflicts can be ended
straightforwardly.
the Ukraine war.
The causes belly of the Ukraine wars,
NATO enlargement,
US coup, CIA operations all over
Ukraine. Even the New York Times
reported that one a couple of months
ago. We've got to stop
being in Russia's face. They know it.
They know all of it. They were so kind
as to post Victoria Nuland's call with
Jeffrey Pott choosing the next
government.
Thank you. They know all of it. They
know who paid for the Maidan
demonstrators. They've got everything.
We've got to stop the provocations.
And yes, by the way, there was no
Russian demand for territory of any
kind. Crimea. They wanted a 25-year
lease, which they negotiated President
Putin uh and President Yanukovich. Not
territory, not a claim. Even after the
coup, Russia took back Crimea. No NATO,
you're not getting that base.
But even when it came to the Donbos,
they just said autonomy
in this postcoo anti-Russia regime. The
United States said no to that one, too.
And incidentally, I'll share with you
just one moment. In 2021, the war could
have been avoided easily by President
Biden saying to President Putin, "NATO
will not expand to Ukraine." And I will
say so.
And I called Jake Sullivan.
He teaches at Harvard.
It's all consistent.
after you fail in Washington.
And I said, Jake, avoid a war.
Stop NATO enlargement. It's ridiculous.
It's useless. Would you like it on the
Rio Grand in Mexico, a a military Mex, a
Russian military base said, "Jeff, we
have an open door policy for NATO."
Said, "Jake, give me a break. Open door
policy."
I repeated the Monroe Doctrine to no
effect and I said, "Jake,
stop the NATO enlargement." He said to
me, "Jeff, NATO's not going to enlarge
to Ukraine."
I said, "Jake, we're going to have a war
over something that's not going to
happen. Why don't you say so?" He said
to me, "Don't worry, there's not going
to be a war."
Honestly, these people are not clever.
They're not clever.
What they're doing makes no sense.
They don't know what they're doing.
We don't know when Biden checked out.
Maybe already then.
But in any event, they're not smart.
They're getting us into trouble.
So, we could make peace in Ukraine.
Tomorrow was yesterday was a hint of it.
But you could see the president is so
everything about our media, about the
Congress, about the military-industrial
complex, he whether he has the skill or
not, I don't know. But if he were a
communicator and had the guts and what
he should stand up and explain to the
American people, this was about NATO
enlargement. We're not going to do it.
That would be the end. But he can't
quite he says it privately, I'm sure,
but not publicly. Why? Because we're
still trapped.
We're trapped as Eisenhower told us
we're trapped.
And all these think tanks up and down
the East Coast are bought the same way.
It's all phony. Everything you hear
about the data. There was a report
recently about Russia's casualties being
x times that of Ukraine by
one of the Washington think tanks. So I
looked at the
it was absurd. So I looked at the
footnote. Where'd that come from? The
footnote came from the uh Ministry of
Defense of Britain. I was already
suspicious. So then I went to the
Ministry of Defense of Britain and after
a little maneuvering track down its
source. It was Ukraine.
Oh my god. They get paid for this. Of
course it's paid propaganda. Okay.
Ukraine can be stopped when the
president of the United States says
publicly NATO will not enlarge. He could
add parenthesis it was a bad idea.
If he wants, he could say, "It wasn't my
idea. It was their terrible ideas." He
could say, "Obama did the coup."
Whatever he wants to say, but if he told
the truth, the war will end. When it
comes to the Middle East,
oh God.
Practically speaking,
we should vote today, tomorrow, Monday
in the UN Security Council for a state
of Palestine alongside the state of
Israel. You'd have aund
[Music]
you would have
192 votes and Israel would not have a
veto and it would be implemented. And I
speak with
top leaders across the world in my job,
including throughout the Middle East,
all of the governments, with Iran, with
the Organization of Islamic Cooperation,
with presidents of Islamic majority
countries all over the world, Indonesia,
Malaysia, throughout Africa. Everybody's
ready for peace
except the zealots in Israel and the
Israel lobby here in the United States.
That's it. And peace could come the
moment we tell the truth and tell them
to stop the genocide. And we stop being
complicit in the genocide, too. It's not
even complicated.
And finally, we are preparing for war
with China. Now, if you want the worst
idea on the whole planet in all of
history, that's it.
Unbelievable that the thought could even
be uttered.
Let me tell you something about China's
overseas military adventures.
It's easy. I'm going to give you 2,000
years of China's overseas military
adventures.
I'm done.
There have never been Chinese overseas
military adventures.
China never invaded Japan once in 2,000
years.
with the following footnote. If anyone
challenges me when you repeat that and
they say, "Sax is an idiot. Doesn't he
know that China invaded Japan in 1274 AD
and 1281 AD?" And you remind them, "No,
no, that was the Mongols, not the
Chinese." Okay?
China never invaded Korea once in 2,000
years
except in 1950 when Douglas MacArthur
threatened nuclear war on China.
Other than that, never.
And yes,
I did get an email from a very nice
Vietnamese correspondent uh uh
corresponder, not correspondent, uh who
said, "Mr. Saxs, you underestimate we've
been at war with China for 2,000 years,
Vietnam."
I had to remind him that the actual war
ended 1,50 years ago
and that there was were two wars in the
last thousand years. It's true. China
did invade a northern province of
Vietnam in for in 1410 AD and the war
lasted for 17 years to for 1427 at which
point the Chinese were defeated by the
Vietnamese and by malaria which is one
of the reasons why they never did it.
There is a disease zone and a tropical
forest zone and a mountain zone. And
they invaded Vietnam one month in 1979
uh after Vietnam had toppled their ally
next door in Cambodia was one month.
Other than that, a thousand years.
China's not going to invade the United
States.
It can't.
It won't.
It's not going to invade any place.
And if there would be an invasion even
of Taiwan, which is a province of China,
it would be because the United States is
unilaterally arming Taiwan
against our diplomacy, against our
treaties, against our 1982 communicate
which said we would phase out arming
Taiwan. The biggest risk we face is
turning Taiwan into Ukraine.
And we're way on the way to doing that
because the same
thought processes in Washington
are at work in East Asia. It's just that
the consequences would be even more
devastating.
First for Taiwan, second for the United
States, and third for the entire world.
So let me end by saying not only could
all these conflicts easily be resolved
easily be resolved but we should also
look just a bit at the process and I
just want to mention uh a few quick
points. First,
it was already recognized by uh
President Truman in 1963 publicly soon
after Kennedy's assassination and
already known before that that the
biggest mistake we made in 1947 was to
give the CIA two jobs. one,
intelligence, which we need, and two,
covert operations, which is absolutely
deadly for our security and for world
peace. We should end all CIA covert
operations. Period.
Second, obviously from the news that
we've seen recently and from what we
know, we need to depoliticize the CIA
and the intelligence agencies. We need
intelligence. We don't need politics in
those agencies.
Third, we need to close our overseas
military bases. They serve.
They are hundreds of billions of dollars
in 80 countries, 750 to 800 overseas
military bases that only suborn politics
all over the world, support covert
operations, and create terrible expense
and terrible crisis.
We need diplomacy to return. Uh JD Vance
explained what he called the uh Trump
doctrine. I just want to say
he got part of it right and one major
part wrong. Or I mean the doctrine is
part right and a major part wrong. Vance
said that the Trump doctrine is first
articulate a clear American interest.
Good. Second aggressively seek a
diplomatic solution. Good. Then the
third, if diplomacy fails, use
overwhelming military force to solve the
issues and then withdraw before it
becomes a a
uh
oh, I don't have the right word, an
extended conflict. Huh?
That is the Iran absurdity at play. By
the way, if that was aggressive
diplomacy, you announce your next
meeting is on Sunday and you bomb on
Friday
and that that's really going to solve
your problems or enhance diplomacy. So
the Trump doctrine, if that's really
what it is, urgently needs to be
rethought. And finally, uh most
importantly, we need public
understanding. We need public awareness.
We need the public to understand what
America's real interests are. We need
brave congressmen like Congressman
Duncan who told his constituency that
these wars make no sense, that they are
not for American security. We need the
Ron Paul Institute. We need our favorite
judge Napoleano. Thank you very much.