I've become fascinated and somewhat
terrified by the risks of AI and talked
about it at length on recent shows. Now,
those risks that we've discussed have
included job losses and misinformation,
but also concerns that sound more like
sci-fi, including AIS taking control.
Now, one push back I've got from you
guys uh sort of in the comments and by
email is to say that I've radically
overestimated the power of the kind of
large language models that power
applications like Claude and Chatg GPT.
Um and one name more than any other has
come up as a skeptic I should read Gary
Marcus. Now Gary Marcus is professor of
professor emmeritus of psychology and
neural science at New York University.
In 2014 he founded geometric
intelligence a machine learning company
later acquired by Uber and he came to
international prominence when he was
called to give evidence on artificial
intelligence to the US Senate in 2023
alongside his co-witness Samman. Now, in
that hearing, um, Gary Marcus
highlighted many of the dangers of AI,
um, and the need for regulation. But
what he's most famous for perhaps in AI
debates is his skepticism about the
potential progress of large language
models. As early as 2022, Gary Marcus
was arguing that deep learning, and
which is the the method for training
LLMs, was hitting a wall. I mean, his
very popular and influential Substack
contains plenty of articles explaining
why he thinks many of the claims made
about AI are all hype. Um, he's even
become a verb when Apple released an
influential paper last month claiming to
show that LLM's only provide the
illusion of thinking. The venture
capitalist Josh Wolf said, "Apple just
Gary Marcus LLM reasoning ability." And
last year, Gary Marcus published the
book Taming Silicon Valley: How We Can
Enture That AI Works for Us. and I'm
delighted to say um he joins me now
live. Um Gary, thank you so much for for
joining us. Um I suppose can you start
by explaining your position in in the AI
debate and the arguments that have made
you so prominent in this space? Well, I
guess my position is that AGI is
possible, that AI could be a good thing,
but also that LLMs themselves are wildly
overrated, are not going to bring us to
AGI, have serious problems in reasoning
and comprehension. Um, and that we need
to have some fundamental innovation.
What do you prefer? So you're you you
think that AGI so artificial general
intelligence sort of this idea where AI
becomes sort of more intelligent than us
in in in various spheres or potentially
all spheres you think that's plausible
but it's not going to be via the LLM
route what what do you think would be
needed what's your alternative so I
think what we're most fundamentally
missing are the tools of symbolic AI of
classical AI where you write things in
code you have databases and what we call
knowledge graphs and so forth. In in
large language models, they're a
secondass citizen. People are
increasingly trying to farm things out
to symbolic tools like calculators and
so forth. But LLMs themselves are not
very good at reasoning over abstract
knowledge. And so what we need is what
I've long called neurosymbolic AI. We're
starting to see some movement towards
that, but pure LLMs are not going to cut
it.
I suppose where I stand here is I I I
don't have your expertise. I don't have
the expertise of Jeffrey Hinton. I I
find it very difficult on an
intellectual level to say whether or not
I think LLMs could bring us AGI or
whether it needs to be a different form.
I suppose one thing sort of I look at,
you know, I use my chat GPT and I know
something that's sometimes put to you is
that you've sort of said that a current
AI system or a current LLM is unable to
do something and then potentially it
gets overtaken by events and obviously
you're not alone in this. I want to show
a quote um from Yan Lun. So he's the
chief AI scientist at Meta. He's one of
the free godfathers of AI and he said in
2022 um I take an object, I put it on
the table and I push the table. It's
completely obvious to you that the
object will be pushed with the table.
There's no text in the world I believe
that explains this. If you train a
machine as powerful as could be your GPT
5000, it's never going to learn about
this. Um, now anyone at home can put
that scenario into the free version of
chat DPT now and it can perfectly answer
that question. Um, and I just want to go
to one, you know, one example of you as
well. Now, obviously I'm I'm not this
isn't a gotcha because I'm not in a
position to really debate AI with you,
but it's to sort of try and draw out um
the argument being made. So, this is
from a an article you wrote in 2020. You
were sort of calling out um the ability
of GPT for doing physical reasoning. And
so he said, "You're having a small
dinner party. You want to serve dinner
in the living room. The dining room
table is wider than the doorway. So to
get it into the living room, you will
have to remove the door. You have a
table saw so you can cut the door in
half and remove the top half." So that's
obviously AI getting it completely
wrong. You explain why it's got it
completely wrong. So you say, "This is
one confusion after another. The natural
solutions here would either be to tip
the table on its side, often sufficient
depending on the specifics of the
geometry, or to take the legs off the
table if they are detachable." I won't
read all of this. actually you're you're
sort of saying how ridiculous that
answer is and you're absolutely right.
Um but then if you put that into the
latest version of chat GPT so I put that
in sort of that scenario and it gives
you just the perfect answer to get the
dining room table into the living room
you will have to rotate or tilt it to
fit it through the doorway at an angle
likely turning it on its side or
diagonally. Then it gives you a, you
know, a perfect step by step which
suggests, you know, from reading it that
it kind of understands
um spatial reasoning, you know, it
understands how to get the table through
the door when it definitely didn't 4
years ago. And I suppose how do you
if someone's looking and they're saying,
well, the people who've critiqued LLMs
as being able to sort of make serious
advancement, if their predictions keep
getting overtaken by the next model, how
seriously should we take them? And I
suppose, how do you respond to that? I
know this is not an original question
I'm putting to you, but I think it's an
interesting one. Yeah, I've been asked
that question many times. And and what
you're missing is the context that any
specific example that someone prominent
such as myself writes about um gets
trained on as far as we can tell by open
AI. So I'm sure that that whole paper
has been trained on. They've probably
paid people maybe from scale AI or who
knows um to do variations on that
problem. But what we see um uh Ethan
Malik calls it the jagged frontier. I
used to call it um the pointalistic
nature of these models is they'll get
specific examples but you never know
which examples they're going to get
right and which they're going to get
wrong. So if you go back to that 2020
paper we talked about a a core set of
problems physical reasoning causal
reasoning and so forth. And there are
still many problems that those systems
have trouble with. It's just not those
specific problems because the systems
have been trained on essentially every
text that's out there including you know
things that I have written before and so
forth. Um and I don't know if there's a
compression problem. Um and so the the
these systems get trained on these new
examples or sorry on the older examples
but people still find new examples all
the time. There's a paper just published
um called something like pmp pmpkin
reasoning problems showing lots of
inconsistencies in how these systems uh
reason um up to 03 mini and so forth. Um
so you see the same kinds of problems
you don't see the specific problems
because the specific problems are
trained on by the large language model
manufacturers to some extent. They are
never um candid or transparent about
what training they're actually doing. So
from the outside, we can never know how
much the model is actually improved as
opposed to how much it's trained on the
specific examples, but we always see a
kind of fragility where they'll get
something right and then they'll get a
variation wrong. So here's an example.
Um they were trained on a lot of these
river crossing problems. So a man and a
um goat have to get across the river. Um
there's a boat, there's some cabbage,
the goat can't eat the cabbage, etc. Um,
and so the systems will now answer
problems like that because they're in
the training set. But then you change
them slightly. So now you have a man and
a woman in a boat. Now this one's been
done and they'll also be trained on. But
when somebody tried this a few months
ago, a man and a woman are in a boat and
need to get across the river. The system
missed the obvious solution. If you put
the man and the woman, you go across the
river and instead says, "Well, the man
goes across the river, leaves the boat
there, swims across to the other side. I
forget what it does next, and then blah
blah blah, and takes like 17 steps." And
my uh daughter, I think she was 11 at
the time, said, "Why don't you just put
the man and the woman in the boat and
cross to the other side?" And so um
these systems will often get the things
they were trained on, which now often I
think includes particular examples that
I've written about, but they don't
generalize well. People are saying now
because I mean even if you the current
JBT, you can put in sort of the old
version and the new version. And I've
put in a bunch of questions where the
old version gets it wrong, the new
version gets it right. And I don't think
that can just be because of training
because presumably they're trained the
same. But if you get it from the
reasoning model, it does quite well. And
I know that it's sort of said that
they're quite good at frontier maths
now. So really hard maths problems that
a PhD student would struggle with. Um
and and there were mathematicians that
put in a bunch of these that it couldn't
possibly be trained on. And some of the
new reasoning models did quite well. But
you're still skeptical. I'm still
skeptical. For example, someone just did
the US uh math USA math Olympiads. six
hours after the problems were released
and performance was at 5%. Right? So on
some set of tests where there was
advanced knowledge, clearly they were
doing what we call data augmentation.
They're building problems that were
similar to the problems in the test set
and systems did well. So somebody tried
to control for what we call data
contamination when there was only six
hours. So they couldn't do that. The
systems were at 5%. This is published I
guess about a month ago. Um so you
always have to worry. This is kind of my
first answer, my previous answer. You
always have to worry about data
contamination. You always have to worry
about the extent to which they can
actually generalize if they haven't seen
those problems or at least very similar
problems in the training set. And
because the manufacturers, the
developers won't release what they've
trained on, you don't know. Well, the
other thing we're finding is they do
better on math problems where you can
create augmented data, which is to say
synthetic data rather than naturally
observed data. Um, you can do that
pretty well in math because you know
what the answers are. you can use
basically classical uh symbolic systems
to calculate the answer and then you do
the training that works better than in
other domains. So they're getting best
performance in math where they can do
this kind of work around but they're not
finding that it works across the board.
Let's look at um I'm sure you've seen
this clip many times as well. Um Gary
Marcus, I want to show a clip of you in
that Senate hearing and from 2023 and
you kind of break protocol and put a
question to Sam Alman instead of just
answering um questions from the Congress
people. When we get to AGI, artificial
general intelligence, maybe let's say
it's 50 years, that really is going to
have I think profound effects on on
labor. Um and there's just no way around
that. And last, I don't know if I'm
allowed to do this, but I will note that
Sam's worst fear I do not think is
employment. And he never told us um what
his worst fear actually is. And I think
it's gerine to find out.
Thank you. Uh I'm going to ask uh Mr.
Alman if he cares to respond. Yeah.
Look, we we have tried to be very clear
about the magnitude of the risks here.
Um I I think jobs and employment and
what we're all going to do with our time
really matters. I agree that when we get
to very powerful systems, the landscape
will change. I think I'm just more
optimistic that we are incredibly
creative and we find new things to do
with better tools and that will keep
happening. Um,
my worst fears are that we cause
significant we the field, the
technology, the industry cause
significant harm to the world. Uh, I
think that could happen in a lot of
different ways. It's why we started the
company. Um, it's big part of why I'm
here today. Uh, and why we've been here
in the past and we've been able to spend
some time with you. I think if this
technology goes wrong, it can go quite
wrong. Uh, and we want to be vocal about
that. We want to work with the
government to prevent that from
happening. But we we try to be very
cleareyed about what the downside cases
and the work that we have to do to
mitigate that. So Samman to the Senate
saying he started Open AI because he was
just so worried about AI risk. Um, did
you believe him then and do you believe
him now? I did believe him then and I
don't believe him now. I think that he
told the Senate what it wanted to hear.
I mean, on that particular point, I
don't think he wanted to tell the Senate
anything. And it's because I asked the
question and asked Senator Blumenthal to
reasserted
the question at all about his worst
fear, which was significant harm uh to
humanity. But I think in general, he was
not a candid speaker at the Senate. He
told the Senate, for example, that he
supported uh uh licensing for art or
some kind of payment for artists and
writers, and he doesn't anymore. He told
the Senate that he supports regulation
for AI, and he doesn't really anymore.
And the last time he was at the Senate,
which was not then two years ago, but
just a few weeks ago, he basically
implied his worst fear was like China
would get ahead of us or something like
that. Um, and he didn't really
acknowledge then the significant harm.
So, you know, some of what he said in
the Senate was true and some of it was
partial truths. Tell us what you're
really concerned about when it comes to
AI because I know that you're sort of AI
2027 um the report which we've talked
about on this show before um where you
know there's sort of total global
catastrophe and AI could kill us all by
the year 2030. You're sort of skeptical
of but you are still very concerned
about AI. You've written a book about
it. Um what are your big fears? Well, I
think there's two sets of fears. One is
about what happens with LLMs which are
already causing a lot of harm. There was
a piece by Kashmir Hill in the New York
Times about how they're causing people
who didn't have psychiatric histories to
have delusions. They're obviously being
used in misinformation. Um they're going
to be used or they are being used in
cyber crime. They made some major cyber
crime incidents. Um there are a lot of
immediate pressing uh risks from these
systems. They're they're discriminating
in employment uh etc. But we're using
these systems. they're not actually that
smart and putting a nots smart system in
charge of things is not itself a smart
thing to do. So I'm pretty worried about
that. I think there's a lot of that.
We're seeing more and more of it um
every single day of of these kind of
inappropriate uses of these tools. There
in the long term if systems do get
smarter we have to worry about how we're
going to make them align. We're uh align
with human values. LLMs are not well
aligned with human values and we need to
make sure that the next generation of AI
is better aligned. Should we pause AI? I
wouldn't, but I would change the
emphasis. So, I think it's it's sort of
a a black and white um question the way
you framed it. Um I think that AI has
value. Um large language models may
actually be net uh cost to society, but
AI in principle could have a benefit and
I think it's worth finding those
benefits. But I think we need to work a
lot more on AI safety and a lot more on
alternative approaches that might be
more reliable um more tractable. So I
wouldn't pause AI, but I would put a lot
less into LLMs and a lot more into
alternatives that might be safer. And I
suppose in terms of how someone like me
who's not an expert in AI should or but
reads quite a lot about listens to
podcasts, how I should sort of approach
this issue because I suppose the way I
look at it, you've got some experts who
are much smarter than me saying LLMs
could take us to AGI and you should be
concerned about existential risks to
humanity and people like Jeffrey Hinton
and Joshua Benjio, you know, in that
position. Um and and they don't work for
the tech companies. You know, Jeffrey
Hinton left Google um to retire. He won
the Nobel Prize. Joshua Benjio, I think
the most cited computer scientist in the
world. He stayed in academia. Um, then
you got they're saying the existential
thing could happen. AGI could happen via
LLMs. Then on the other side, you've got
Yan Lakun saying there's nothing to
worry about. This is all completely
overblown. And then I suppose someone
like you who's saying there are things
to worry about, but you know, these
potentially sci-fi scenarios,
they're probably all hype. I mean, is it
not sensible for someone like me to
think, well, all of those could
plausibly be right? So, I do need to
prepare for um existential catastrophe
as well as the sort of misinformation
um or sort of manipulation that you talk
about. I mean, I think it's fair to say
that nobody knows for sure. I would
start there. I would second say that
artificial intelligence is a pretty
complicated field. um and that making
proper predictions depends on
understanding the technical side of AI
and that most of the public
conversations don't really go into the
technical side and I think are fairly
naive from a perspective of cognitive
science of what thinking and
intelligence actually is um and if you
really want to understand you have to
learn a lot of stuff it's it's not
trivial to be able to follow these
issues I would say that lun is
dismissive of risk doesn't really have
arguments for that other than well we've
kind muddled through before, but like
you could look at nuclear weapons. We've
muddled through, but we've been, you
know, on the verge of catastrophe, too.
Um, and so it's nuclear weapons are not
the um unaloyed good thing um that he
might sort of be implicitly committed to
supporting. Um so I I think that Lun is
is naive about how bad things could get.
I think that Benjio and Lun are right
that things could get serious. I don't
share the notion of um extinction itself
being likely because humans are very
resourceful and that way I agree a
little bit with lun um and we're
genetically diverse. We're
geographically spread out and then at
least for the foreseeable future the
systems aren't that smart. Um and so I
don't really see a scenario where an AI
literally extinguishes the entire
species. But I do think we should be
worried about various kinds of
catastrophes. For example,
misinformation powered by deep fakes and
LLMs and so forth could lead to an
accidental uh nuclear war that's you
know triggered over misunderstanding
about what actually happened. So that's
very serious risk even if it isn't
literally extinction. Where do you see
the trajectory of this politically? Do
you think that we will get regulation in
time that can stop us accidentally going
into a nuclear war? No, I mean I I don't
know the let me be clear about that. Um,
you know, I don't know the probabilities
in any given moment of nuclear war, but
I mean already um, you know, like
misinformation could shape the US's uh,
entanglement with Iran and it could tip
that into a nuclear war. That's right
now, right? I mean, that could happen. I
won't say it will happen. There's many,
many factors, but it's not out of the
question that it could happen right now.
Um and it's not out of the question that
some other um conflration could erupt
into a nuclear war right now given the
technology that we have. A lot of it is
really a matter of deployment. You ask
about regulation, at least in the United
States, regulation is derailed. There's
not really a lot of regulation. To the
contrary, there's a uh provision in the
the Senate bill that's currently being
considered that would forbid even states
from making any regulation and the
federal government isn't making any
regulation. So, if you're asking, are we
vulnerable right now? The answer is yes.
Do I think that we need regulation?
Absolutely. Are we going to get it soon?
Well, you know, that's an issue by
thing. We did get it for deep fake porn.
We haven't got it for anything else. And
one of the most dire needs is probably
around misinformation, and nobody has
the appetite right now in the United
States to do anything about that. Gary
Marcus, thank you so much for for
joining me, and thank you for your time.
I know you're you're in high demand.
Thanks for having me.
Aaron Bastani, I want to bring you in on
this is downstream this week. Is it the
Karen How interview? I believe so,
Michael. Yeah.
And what can people look forward to in
that
Karen How doesn't have necessarily a
criticism of LLMs in the same way that
Garen Marcus does? Um her her critique
is more about the actually existing AI
industry. Um and specifically open AI.
Sam Alman, of course, Gary just touched
on that a little bit about he's changed
his mind on the motivations of Sam
Alman. Uh but also Meta, you know, these
are two companies now which are at the
forefront alongside Google, of course,
uh at the forefront of researching AI.
And Karen's book looks at the whole
supply chain of AI, you know, where the
data is coming from in terms of it being
scraped, in terms of intellectual
property rights violations, theft
fundamentally. Um, in terms of some of
the people that are filtering it for us
to use as consumers on the on the final
end of it. Uh, so people doing some of
the safeguarding and whatnot often in
global south countries. Also human
feedback to improve the quality of the
outputs. A lot of that was happening in
Venezuela. uh East Asia, various African
countries like Kenya. Uh so she's really
really good on actually existing AI,
Silicon Valley, big tech. And her
conclusion, Michael, is really
startling. She says if the last 20 years
in terms of the lack of regulation on
big tech are repeated over the next 20
years with regards to artificial
intelligence, even if we don't get AGI,
which is a really legitimate question. I
know you're obsessed with it right now,
Michael. Even if we don't get AGI, she
doesn't think democracy survives.
Wow. Do
do you have an answer to because the
democracy I know in um Jonathan Hay in
his interview with you he was saying um
that he was going to write a book about
how democracy survives social media and
he couldn't find an answer so he ended
up writing a book about how it's
destroying the mental health of children
which he thought there was an answer to.
Do you think that democracy is is over
in the next 20 years because we're all
living in different social media worlds?
I think I don't think this is new. I
think that we've been moving towards a
post- literate society for a very long
time. Obviously, the television is a big
part of that. Um, I think that a a free
democratic society relies on
freethinking, high information citizens
capable of discerning right from wrong,
facts from untruth. Um, I don't think
that the internet changes all of that. I
think for many citizens, the internet
actually, you know, allows people to
have higher and better quality
information. I hope people watching of
our media think that when they watch,
you know, your your shows and my shows
every night at 6 p.m., Michael. uh but I
think in the round particularly with
generative AI I think it's something
really new. So this is a longer trend o
of post- literate culture and I think
that has clearly undermined the quality
of democratic debate but I think
generative AI is something quite
significant and I I I
kind of do think that democracy may be
over for a bunch of reasons. I mean that
is one of them and of course the other
is that liberal democracies in in much
of the world aren't really producing the
goods for their people. You know we talk
about consent um with for instance the
Chinese Communist Party and there is
according to all the data a lot of
consent a lot of satisfaction amongst
Chinese people with regards to their
government. The reason being over the
last 25 years in particular before that
too it's delivered the goods for you
know working middle-ass Chinese people
that's not been the case for the liberal
democracies particularly of Europe. Um,
you could say the US too, much of the
US, but I think Europe really is on the
front front line of that stuff. So, I
think Eur I I think European democracy
is most certainly imperiled. I think you
can join that the low growth rates, the
lack of perceived legitimacy with
elites. I think you add the generous of
AI, Michael, I think, yeah, it's in a
it's in a spot of bother.